James Dugan papers, 1933-1977 00242
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
James Dugan papers
1933-1977
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
00242
45 Cubic feet 15 audio-visual items.
James Dugan graduated from the Pennsylvania State College with a degree in journalism in 1937. He became a noted underwater explorer and wrote more than ten books, three of which were in collaboration with the noted French oceanographer, Captain Jacques-Yves Cousteau.
The collection of the papers of undersea explorer and author James Dugan includes articles, 15 audio-visual items, information files, research materials, correspondence, photographs, manuscripts and proofs for publications, and scrapbooks.
Biographical Note
James Dugan (1912-1967) was born in Altoona, Pennsylvania, and graduated from Altoona High School in 1929. In the mid-thirties, he graduated from the Pennsylvania State College with a degree in journalism. As an undergraduate, Dugan served on the staff of many campus publications. He was editor-in-chief of the literary magazine, Old Main Bell and later became editor of the campus humor magazine, Penn State Froth. Lynn Christy, a 1935 graduate from Penn State, commented that Dugan brought a heightened awareness of socio-economic pressures to the Bell and his "Claycatures" to Froth. Claycatures were lifelike caricatures modeled in clay and then photographed for magazine use. Frequently they were featured in articles lampooning faculty, administration and student leaders. During World War II, Dugan served with the 8th Army in Europe and contributed to the Army publications, Yank and Salute. Soon after Paris was liberated from the Nazis during World War II, Dugan met the French oceanographer Jean-Jacques Cousteau and later participated with him in a number of undersea explorations. After the war, he wrote articles for such magazines as the Saturday Evening Post, Holiday, New York Times Magazine and National Geographic. He became an author on ship and sea subjects and was a noted underwater explorer. Dugan wrote more than ten books, three of which were in collaboration with the noted French oceanographer, Captain Jacques-Yves Cousteau. A major venture was the Calypso Marine Archeological Expedition of Grand Conglove Islands from 1952 to 1954. This expedition recovered an ancient Greek amphora, or wine jar, from a third century B. C. cargo vessel. Dugan presented the amphora to Penn State prior to his death in 1967. His first major work, The Great Iron Ship, published in 1953, was a Book-of-the-Month Club selection and the basis for a three-part serial in the New Yorker magazine. Among his other writings are Ploest, written in collaboration with Carroll Stewart, The Great Mutiny, The Living Sea and "Man Under the Sea." He also wrote the narrative for the film based on Jacques-Yves Cousteau's book, The Silent World, exhibited at the World Theater in 1956. Dugan held memberships with the Undersea Advisory Board of the Philadelphia Maritime Museum and the French Benevolent Society founded by Benjamin Franklin. In 1967, Dugan died in his quarters aboard a research vessel in the Gulf of Mexico. The submarine was stationed there for Dugan and associates to obtain material for a National Geographic Society book.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Moving Image; Photographic; Scrapbooks; Cartographic; Graphic
- Articles, 1
  - Albatross, chapter from American Viking (6 copies), 1963; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Chatelaine Magazine, Kathleen Dunning, 1954/06; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - College Life, New Pioneers, 1965/04; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Colliers Magazine, Fish (tear sheet), 1955/09/16; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Constellation Magazine, Cousteau, Gas Line Route, 1959/11; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Daily Telegraph Magazine, Farming Sea Bed (2 Copies), 1968/05/24; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Holiday Magazine, Department of Commerce (full issue & tear sheet), 1962/09; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Holiday Magazine, John Ledyard (tear sheet), 1960/10; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Holiday Magazine, Mayor Daley's Chicago, 1963/12; 2 Items (Box 2)
  - Holiday Magazine, Smithsonian, 1960/07; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Holiday Magazine, What's Going on Underwater, 1965/06; 2 Items (Box 2)
  - Life, Underwater Wonders (tear sheets), 1950/11/27; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Canasta (full issue and tear sheets), 1952/03/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Cunard Line, Part 1 (tear sheets), 1950/08/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Cunard Line, Part 2 (tear sheets), 1950/08/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Danny Kaye (tear sheets), 1950/09/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Dean Tait of Vassar (tear sheets), 1950/07/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Gayelord Hauser, bylined James Edgar, 1951/02/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, How to Miss the Mobs, 1952/02/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Jack Kash, 1951/02/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, L.B. Mayer, 1953/04/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Levitt House, 1952/05/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Marie Dressler, 1952/03/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Matilda Etches (tear sheets), 1950/03/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Mickey Spillane, 1952/04/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Robert Fontain (tear sheets), 1950/03/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Sandwiches, 1952/10/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Soups, 1953/04/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Tin Pan Alley (tear sheets), 1950/09/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Turkey, 1951/12/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Vets of Future Wars (tear sheets), 1950/06/01; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Maclean's Magazine, Walt Kelly, bylined Harrison Fisher (tear sheets), 1950/04/15; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Male Magazine, Ploesti, 1963/02; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - New York Times Magazine, Diving for Sunken Treasure, 1961/03/12; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - New York Times Magazine, Portrait of Homo Aquaticus, 1963/04/21; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Oceans, New Pioneers, 1969/03; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Park East Magazine, Hamptons, 1952/08; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Park East Magazine, Home Brewed Shoes, 1952/04; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Park East Magazine, New York 20, 1953/03; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Playboy Magazine, Nor Any Drop to Drink (full issue and tear shts), 1966/09; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Reader's Digest, Fish Named Ulysses (tear sheets), 1963/09; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Beer Drinkers, 1947/08; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Giles and City that Ducked, 1946/04; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Henry Wallace, 1947/11; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, James Mason, 1947/07; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Lon Levy, 1947/09; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, New Yorkers are Nuts, 1947/12; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, No Vacancies, 1946/09; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Train Robbery, 1946/12; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Salute Magazine, Trouble with College, 1947/06; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Skin Diver Magazine, Dumas Dives Doria, 1974/08; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Star Weekly Magazine, Little French Club, 1962/02/03; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Sunday Bulletin Magazine, Pioneer in Philadelphia, 1964/01/12; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Technocrat, Nor any Drop to Drink, 1967/03; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - True Magazine, Great Iron Ship (tear sheet), 1960/11; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Twenty-one Magazine, Dumas Manfish, 1951/08; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Underwater Reporter, Bulletin of Underwater Society (4 copies), 1965/05; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yachting Magazine, 3-Dimensional Yachting (full issue, tear sheet), 1967/03; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Alexander, 1945/06/22; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, At Old Swing U., 1945/08/17; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Atlee, 1945/09/28; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, First Election in Ten Years, 1945/06/29; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Flynnberg and the Bond Sale, 1945/09/14; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Flynnberg Meets a Lord, 1945/09/14; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Flynnberg on Supply, 1945/09/07; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, France Sweats it Out, 1945/02/11; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Mathis brothers, 1943/08/08; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Prime Minister from Limehouse, 1945/08/31; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Propaganda Mule, 1943/12/19; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Red Air Force, 1945/02/04; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Yak, Yak, or Lhasa's in Cold, Cold Ground, 1945/08/10; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - Yank Magazine, Zhukov, 1945/07/06; 1 Items (Box 2)
  - American Viking - Saga of Hans Isbrandtsen, 1963; 1 Items (Box 3)
  - Living Sea - Hamilton and Harper Galleys, 1963; 1 Items (Box 3)
  - Living Sea-Manuscript, 1963; 5 Items (Box 3)
  - Air Power Historian, German Defense and Allied Ineteligence, 1962/01; 1 Items (Box 4)
  - Le Petit Club Français, undated; 1 Items (Box 4)
  - Penn State Froth, 1933-1937; 1 Items (Box 4)
  - Transactions, Calypso Oceanographic Expeditions, 1955/10; 1 Items (Box 4)
  - Conshelf III - draft articles, undated; 2 Items (Box 7)
  - Bibliographies, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Biographical Material, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - British Navy, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Great Mutiny, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Lexography, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Mutinies correspondence, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Mutiny Illustrations, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Philadelphia, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Philadelphia - Why We Moved to, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Sandwiches, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Silent World, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Smithsonian Institution, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Soup, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Space Shoes, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Tin Pan Alley - Howie Richmond, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Toronto Weekend, 1958; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Treasury, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Turkey, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Ungava, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Vets of Future Wars, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - World Series, undated; 1 Items (Box 14)
  - Atlas, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Diving Guide, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - New York $5, 000, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Quiet Evening, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Sleep, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Story Ideas, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Twentieth Century Show, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Underwater Newsletter, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Underwater Yearbook, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - US Divers, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Wartime Pieces, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - World Without Sun, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm (Box 16)
  - World Without Sun Book, undated; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Yearbook, 1963; 1 Items (Box 16)
  - Aldabra, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Bonnard, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Clippings MOD, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Coelacanthe, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Divers' Reception, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - First Annual Convention of Skindivers Program Book, 1959; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Greek Ship, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Incidental Data, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Jr Science Symposia, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Publisher, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Queen Mary Science Walls, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Seychelles Letter, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Symposium (Proposed for Philadelphia), 1962; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Underwater Society of America, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - USA Conventions, 1961-1963; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - USA Founding Convention and Council Unity Meet, 1959; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - USA Mexican Convention, undated; 1 Items (Box 17)
  - Biographical Data, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Conshelf I - III, undated; 3 Items (Box 26)
  - Cruises, 1954-1955; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Deep Star DSL, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Deep Submergence Systems, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Diving Saucer, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Indian Ocean Cruise Notes, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - MTS Convention Daily, 1966/06/28; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Palomares Bomb, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Research Correspondence, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Vessels, Oceano, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Westinghouse, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Articles, undated; 1 Items (Box 30)
  - Man-Made Gill, 1966; 1 Items (Box 37)
  - Articles, undated; 1 Items (Box 42)
- Audio Visual Materials, 2
  - Atlantic Drill - Reel 1, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Chaplin, Charlie Old-Time Comedies, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Deck Diversions Aden Passage - Reel 2, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Flying Enterpise Original - Reel 1 - 5, undated; 5 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Flying Enterprise II - Reels 3, 5, undated; 2 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Mahabalipuram India - Reel 3, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Mahabalipuram India Original, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Portland Captains Panama - Reel 5, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
  - Swim Pool, Ship's Karachi Discharge - Reel 3, undated; 1 Items; Moving Image--Film--16mm
- Correspondence, 3
  - Correspondence, undated; 1 Items (Box 1)
  - Great Iron Ship, 1960; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Great Iron Ship, Fan Letters, 1960; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Living Sea correspondence, 1960; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Men Under Water correspondence, 1960; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Mutiny Under the Sea Correspondence, 1950; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Ploesti Correspondence, 1960; 1 Items (Box 6)
  - Silent World correspondence, 1950; 2 Items (Box 6)
  - City of Chicago - Office of Mayor, 1963/05/20; 1 Items (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1963/05/03; 1 Items (Box 10)
  - Daley, Richard Mayor, 1963; 2 Items (Box 10)
  - Research Correspondence, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Trip material, undated; 3 Items (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1963; 1 Items (Box 28)
  - Publisher Correspondence, 1952-1973; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1967; 1 Items (Box 37)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1973; 1 Items (Box 37)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1966; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Magazine - General Correspondence, 1949-1963; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - National Geographic - Correspondence I and II, 1953-1980; 2 Items (Box 39)
  - Diver Correspondence, 1952-1965; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Fan Letters, 1960-1965; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - WAC Meetings, 1967; 1 Items (Box 42)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1959; 1 Items (Box 44)
- Drawings, 4
  - Cartoon Drawings, undated; 1 Items; Graphic--Posters (Box 1)
  - Plan of Action off Camperdown, undated; 1 Items (Box 1)
  - Proof Sheets, undated; 1 Items; Photographic (Box 1)
  - Scuba Diver, undated; 1 Items; Graphic--Artwork--Drawings (Box 1)
  - Ship Engine, undated; 1 Items; Graphic--Artwork--Drawings (Box 1)
  - Ship Sketch, undated; 1 Items; Graphic--Artwork--Drawings (Box 1)
  - Underwater Layout, undated; 2 Items; Graphic--Artwork--Drawings (Box 1)
- Information Files, 5
  - Borscht Circuit, undated; 1 Items (Box 4)
  - Aquariums, undated; 1 Items (Box 7)
  - Archeological Institute of America, undated; 1 Items (Box 7)
  - Archeology, undated; 3 Items (Box 7)
  - Atomic Waste, undated; 1 Items (Box 7)
  - Atomic Waste Conference, undated; 1 Items (Box 7)
  - Bathyscaphes, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Bells, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Bibliographies Catalogues, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Boats, Boating, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Boats, Plastic, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Boutan - Portier, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Cartoons, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Caves - Cave Diving, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Coast and Geodetic Survey, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Congress and Oceanography, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Cores, Sampling and Dredging, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Current Studies, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Darwin, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Davis, Sir Robert, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Deep Scattering Layer, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diver Down Flag, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diver Training, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Divers and Monsters, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Articles, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Cartoons, Advertising, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Gear Equipment, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Laws, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Medicine, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Diving Scientists, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Engineering, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - English Civilian Diving History, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Expenditions - IGY, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Fatalities, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Fish Behavior Tests, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Flip Ships, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Foundations, undated; 1 Items (Box 20)
  - Gadgets, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Galerne, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Haas, Han, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Helium Diving, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Hollywood, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Hunting, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Icebergs, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - India, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - International Oceanographic Congress, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Inventories, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Japan, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Jenks, Jackson, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Keller, Hannes, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Kenyon and Lallemand, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Maps, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Milne - Edwards, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Mines, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Monitor Wreck, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Murray, Sir John, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Museums, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Navy Diving History, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Neige and Glace Clips, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Observation Chambers, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Oceanography, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Oil Recco, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Pearling, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Personalities, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Philadelphia - Oceanography, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Philadelphia - Reconstruction, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Philadelphia Port of, undated; 1 Items (Box 21)
  - Deep Dives Record, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Diamonds, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - NF Clips, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Photography - Cameras, Film, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Physiology, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Publishing, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Recreation, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Resources, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Safety, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Salvage, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Sea Limits, Fishing Rights, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Sharks, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Shells, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Ship Specifications, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Shipping, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Signs, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Sled, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Sonar, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Soviet, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Stations, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Submarines - Early, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Submarines, Midget, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Submarines, Nuclear, undated; 1 Items (Box 22)
  - Submarines at War, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Submarines, Sunken, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Suez Clearing, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Television Underwater, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Texas Towers, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Tidal Waves, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Treasurer, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Tuna, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - US Civilian Diving History, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Vasa, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Water Production, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Whales, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Wrecks, undated; 1 Items (Box 23)
  - Bibliographical Data, undated; 1 Items (Box 26)
  - Calypso Applicants, undated; 1 Items (Box 28)
  - Calypso Programs - Itins, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Calypso, Blueprint Specifications, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Cartoons, Toys Tie-ins, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Conquest of Inner Space - TV, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - I-Boat, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Motion Pictures, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Movie Sale, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Musee Oceanographique, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Notes and Schedules, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Photographs, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Pipeline Survey, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Publicity Clips, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Requests, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Scientific Reports, Calypso, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Supplies, undated; 1 Items (Box 29)
  - Kerkam, Earl, undated; 1 Items (Box 30)
  - Academy of Arts and Sciences, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - American Geophysical Union, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - American Standards Association, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Anti-Interplanetary Society, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Canadian Club, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Cape Haze Marine Laboratory, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - CEDAM, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - CMAS, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Council of Underwater Archeology, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - French Club, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Inner Space, Inc., undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - Institute of Marine Sciences, undated; 1 Items (Box 31)
  - General Information: R - Z, undated; 6 Items (Box 34)
  - Penn State University, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Putnam's, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Random House, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Schebeko, Marie, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Sea Grant Programs, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Stewart, Cal, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Throckmorton, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Westinghouse, undated; 1 Items (Box 34)
  - Albatross, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Albert, Prince, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Croquet, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - FERG Meeting, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Fiction, General, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Frost Fair and Hiram Sherman Comedy Show, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Guest of Nation and History of Campaign that Failed, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Hilton Head, South Carolina, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Housing - Met Life, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Magnetoys - Sketches, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Monaco, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Photographs, Printing, Postage, Stationery, Supplies Repairs, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Rivers, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Short Fiction, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Short Stories - Humor, 1940; 3 Items (Box 35)
  - VERNE, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Westinghouse Suit, undated; 1 Items (Box 35)
  - Lectures, Television and Radio Appearances, 1954-1961; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Lee, Owen, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Light's Organization, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Maclean's Magazine, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - National Geographic - Research Committee, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - National Geographic Bulletins, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Navy Electronics Lab, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - Nogi Awards, undated; 1 Items (Box 39)
  - American Littoral Society, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Aquadro, Chas, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Collins Construction, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Columbia Pictures, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Coudert, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Diving Equipment and Dealers, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Dumas, F., undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Eastman Kodak, undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - Edgerton, H.E., undated; 1 Items (Box 40)
  - General Information: A - P, undated; 16 Items (Box 40)
  - Edo Corporation, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Encyclopedia Americana, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Feinberg, Walter, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Flaherty, Robert, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - French Government, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - General Electric, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Greene, Elaine, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Harpers I and II, undated; 2 Items (Box 41)
  - Jackson, Phyllis, undated; 1 Items (Box 41)
  - Research Committee Meetings, 1954; 1 Items (Box 42)